A Guide to the Papers of Louise Imogen Guiney, 1885-1918
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
A Guide to the Papers of Louise Imogen Guiney 1885-1918
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7088-a
73 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited by Clifton Waller Barrett on December 17, 1963, and accessioned on September 3, 1964.
Biographical/Historical Information
Louise Imogen Guiney was born January 7, 1861 in Roxbury, Mass., the daughter of Patrick Robert Guiney (January 15,1835-March 21,1877) and Jeannette Margaret Doyle Guiney. Guiney died November 2, 1920 in Chipping Campden, England.
Her father served in the Union army during the Civil War, was brevetted brigadier-general of volunteers in 1864, and died from the effects of a wound that he received in the Battle of the Wilderness. Louise was graduated from Elmhurst Academy, Providence, Rhode Island, in 1879. Her earliest literary work appeared in the Boston Post and the Boston Courier; in 1887 she was a contributor to Harper's, Scribner's, and the Atlantic Monthly.
Her works include: Songs at the Start (1884, poetry); Goose-Quill Papers (1885, essays); The White Sail and Other Poems (1887, poetry); Brownies and Bogles (1888, poetry); Monsieur Henri: A Foot-Note to French History (1892, essays); A Roadside Harp (1893, poetry); A Little English Gallery (1895, essays); Robert Louis Stevenson (1895, biography, with Alice Brown); Lovers' Saint Ruth's and Three Other Tales (1895, short stories); Nine Sonnets Written at Oxford (1895, poetry); Patrins (1897, essays); England and Yesterday (1898, poetry); The Martyrs' Idyl and Shorter Poems (1899, poetry); Robert Emmet (1904); The Princess of the Tower (1906, poetry); Blessed Edmund Campion (1908); Happy Ending (1909, poetry, her collected verse); Letters (1926, letters); Recusant Poets (1939, ed., with Geoffrey Bliss)
Scope and Content
The collection contains the manuscripts of several poems including "The recruit," "A talisman," "Davy," "For a grave in Glasnevin," and "Gloucester Harbor."
Correspondents include William S. Braithwaite, Beverly Chew, Percy J. Dobell, Helen Fish, Richard Watson Gilder, Harper & Brothers, Houghton, Mifflin Co., Robert Underwood Johnson, Arthur W. Kelly, John Lane, Herbert Newman Mozley, Ella Farman Pratt, Edmund C. Richards, Clinton Scollard, Edmund Clarence Stedman, Herbert Pelham Williams, and James C. Young.
The collection also contains a photograph of Guiney, and a clipping of photographs of her mother and of her father Patrick R. Guiney in his Civil War uniform, and a newspaper portrait of her.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series: Manuscripts, Letters, and Photographs and Drawings. Items are arranged chronologically within each series.
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Begins: "Let claws of lightening clutch me..." 1892 September, AMsS poem
  - "The Recruit" 1899 November 4, AMsS poem
  - "A Talisman" 1914 July, AMsS poem
  - "Davy" n.d., AMsS poem
  - "For a Grave in Glasnevin" n.d., AMsS poem
  - "Gloucester Harbor" n.d., AMsS poem
- Series II: Letters
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mrs. Pratt 1885, 4 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mrs. Pratt 1886 August 8, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Bates 1886 September 11, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Scollard 1887 March 6, 3 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mrs. Pratt 1887 May 20, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mrs. Pratt 1887 December 15, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Stedman 1888 December 31, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Waite 1891 February 25, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mrs. Pratt 1891 April 4, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Wingate 1891 June 8, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Parch 1893 May 13, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Arthur W. Kelly 1893 August 4, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Professor Norton [with typewritten copy] 1893 September 25, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Houghton, Mifflin & Co. 1894 February 8, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Harper & Brothers 1894 July 16, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Harper & Brothers 1894 August 9, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Peirce 1894 September 23, 3 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Herbert P. Williams 1896 January 25, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Miller [1896] July 28, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Miss Bridgman 1897 March 10, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Scott 1897 September 24, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Ernest Dressel North [with envelope] 1898 August 3, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Gilder 1899 March 20, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to M.S. O'Donnell 1899 November 4, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to M.S. O'Donnell 1900 October 21, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to M.S. O'Donnell 1900 October 28, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Field 1901 March 31, 2 pp. ALS [original pasted in Patrins by Guiney, 1897, Barrett PS1767.P3 1897]
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Young 1901 April 28, 2 pp. ALS [original pasted in Louise Imogene Guiney Her Life & Works, 1861-1920 by Tenison (Barrett PS1768.T4 1923)]
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to H.N. Morley 1902 September 11, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Gilder 1904 November 27, 3 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Miss Fish [with envelope] 1905 April 8, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to [John] Lane 1905 December 9, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Braithewaite 1906 August 4, 3 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to R.U. Johnson 1906 September 20, APCS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Beverly Chew [with envelope] 1910 April 23, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Beverly Chew [with envelope] [1910] April 28, 2 pp. ANS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Beverly Chew [with envelope] 1910 May 2, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to [?] 1910 June 14, 2 pp. ALS [original pasted in A Renegade Poet and Other Essays by Francis Thompson (Barrett PS1767.T4 1910)]
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to "Dearest Florence" 1910 October 3, 3 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to M.S. O'Donnell 1911 January 26, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Gertrude 1912 February 24, 2 pp. ALS [original in Some Poems of Lionel Johnson with an introduction by Guiney (Barrett PS1767.A16 .J6 1912)]
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Rev. E.C. Richards [with envelope] 1914 October 4, 4 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Percy J. Dobell 1918 December 15, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Johnson February 8, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Wells February 15, 1 p. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Best July 4, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Widdy October 1, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Young October 26, 2 pp. ALS [original pasted in Tenison's Louise Imogene Guiney
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to M.S. O'Donnell November 23, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to James C. Young December 19, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Mr. Schmidt Sunday, 2 pp. ALS
  - Louise Imogene Guiney to Rev. Edmund C. Richards [with envelope] Sunday, 7 pp. ALS
- Series III: Photographs and Drawings
  - Louise Imogene Guiney - standing [taken by James Notman Studio, Boston] n.d., Photo
  - Louise Imogene Guiney - drawing, taken from Meteyard's original [newsclipping] n.d., Drawing
  - Photos of her father, Colonel Patrick R. Guiney in his Civil War uniform, and of her mother, Mrs. Patrick R. Guiney [newsclippings] n.d., Photos